{"tossups": [{"question": "An emir of this city, known in China as Su-fei-er, settled 5300 of his people in China in 1070 to fight the Liao on the invitation of Emperor Shenzong. This city was the birthplace of Naqshbandi Sufism. It\u2019s not Samarkand or Carthage, but legend about a fortress in this city claims that it was built by Siyavash in the area contained within an ox skin as a condition for marrying the daughter of Afrasiab. A group modelled off the Young Turks invited the Soviet conquest of this city and was given prominent leadership positions in the short-lived Soviet republic (*) centered on this city. This city was where Arthur Conolly, coiner of the term \u201cGreat Game\u201d, was killed outside of the Ark Fortress after being accused of spying for the British. Once second only to Baghdad as cultural center of the Islamic world, for 10 points, name this Uzbek city home to Avicenna.", "answer": "Bukhara", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Bukhara</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Bukhara", "Bukhara"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Country Club Dispute was a prolonged conflict that resulted from this action. The Mesilla Valley was a prime target of this action. The failure to build a railroad across the Isthmus of Tehuantepec was an important impetus for this action. This action included a provision for reparations for Indian raids from one of the involved parties into the other. This action was carried out by a former president of the (*) South Carolina Canal and Railroad Company and was largely initiated for the purpose of building a transcontinental railroad that would benefit the South. For 10 points, name this 1854 transaction between the US and Mexico that saw the transfer of nearly 30,000 sq. miles of territory.", "answer": "Gadsden Purchase", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Gadsden Purchase</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Gadsden Purchase", "Gadsden Purchase"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This place held the armor of Henry II of France until 1946 and since the 19th century contains frescoes by Moritz von Schwind depicting scenes from this place\u2019s history. Louis the Springer had soil from his domain brought to the site of this building so that he could claim it lay on his land. Heinrich Raspe expelled his nephew and the boy\u2019s mother, Elizabeth of Hungary, from this place upon the death of his brother in the Sixth Crusade. (*) Wolfram von Eschenbach won a contest called the S\u00e4ngerkrieg at this place, an event that inspired Wagner\u2019s Tannh\u00e4user. This place\u2019s most famous resident stayed here under the pseudonym \u201cJunker J\u00f6rg\u201d and undertook a famous translation of the New Testament. For 10 points, name this Thuringian castle, the home of a recently exiled Martin Luther.", "answer": "Wartburg Castle", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Wartburg</u></b> Castle", "acceptable": ["Wartburg Castle", "Wartburg"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This state provided the larger part of the force that massacred hundreds of people performing the Serpent Dance on the Patio of the Dances. This confederation of four city-states was ruled by a council of teteuctin. A famous warrior from this polity was forced to become a general for his former enemies, in which capacity he took the city of Tangimora from the Pur\u00e9pechas, and was eventually sacrificed after fighting numerous soldiers while chained to a (*) temacalatl stone. This home of Tlahuicole was brought into its most famous alliance by Xicotencatl (\u201cshee-ko-TAYN-cahtle\u201d) the Elder and Maxixcatl (\u201cmah-SHEESH-cahtle\u201d). This polity is most famous for allying with Cort\u00e9s in the destruction of Tenochtitlan. For 10 points, identify this polity, the namesake of a modern Mexican state and one of the primary rivals of the Aztecs.", "answer": "Tlaxcala (\u201ctlahsh-KAH-lah\u201d) or Tlaxcall\u0101n", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tlaxcala or Tlaxcall\u0101n</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tlaxcala or Tlaxcall\u0101n", "Tlaxcala or Tlaxcall\u0101n"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "\u201ctlahsh-KAH-lah\u201d"}, {"question": "17th century historian Ahmed Mohammed al-Maqqari claimed that a polymath of this people was able to fly by attaching feathers to himself and that his only design flaw was not adding a tail to smooth the landing. A queen of this people named Dihya supposedly lived to be 127 years old and led the failed resistance against Musa bin Nusayr. English pirate Jack Ward introduced square-rigged ships to this people. The trade routes whose northern terminus was in the city of Sijilmasa linked this people to the salt mines of (*) Taghaza. The 22nd and 23rd dynasties of Egypt were ruled by people whom the Egyptians called Meshwesh, likely of this ethnic group from Libya. People of this ethnic group have included Massinissa and St. Augustine of Hippo. For 10 points, who are this people who ruled the Almohad Empire and name the coast of the northwest Africa?", "answer": "Berbers (accept Mazigh or Imazighen; prompt on Moors, Libyans, Numidians; do not accept Arabs)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Berbers</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Berbers", "Berbers"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Mazigh or Imazighen; prompt on Moors, Libyans, Numidians; do not accept Arabs"}, {"question": "While besieged by Stjepan Kosa\u010da (\u201cstyeh-pahn ko-sah-chah\u201d) in 1451, this city offered 15,000 ducats, a castle, and a hereditary lordship to anyone who killed him, scaring Kosa\u010da into lifting the siege. This city sold a 12 mile piece of land containing the city of Neum in 1699, which now comprises one country\u2019s only access to the sea. The city of Lausa was incorporated into this city when they were connected by the Stradun. Auguste de Marmont was appointed duke of this city in 1808 for pacifying it and the surrounding region for Napoleon. This city was under (*) Venetian suzerainty from the early 13th century until relinquished to Hungary in a treaty named for the nearby city of Zadar. For 10 points, name this Croatian city, the center of the Republic of Ragusa.", "answer": "Dubrovnik (accept Ragusa before mentioned)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Dubrovnik</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Dubrovnik", "Dubrovnik"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Ragusa before mentioned"}, {"question": "After a massive flood, a city of this civilization created a massive dock/warehouse complex that allowed 30 ships of 50 tons each to unload goods at the same time. This civilization is known for its export of fine carnelian beads. The port of Sutkagen-Dor was likely a stopping point for merchants from this civilization trading with cultures to the west. From its colony at Shortugai, this civilization provided the ancient world with its only source of (*) lapis lazuli. One of this civilization\u2019s primary ports was Lothal and one of its few imports were pearls from Dilmun. Merchants from this civilization carried personalized seals, which provide most known examples of this civilization\u2019s yet undeciphered script. Known as Meluhha in Mesopotamia, for 10 points, identify this first civilization on the Indian subcontinent.", "answer": "Harappan Civilization (accept Indus Valley Civilization or IVC)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Harappan</u></b> Civilization", "acceptable": ["Harappan Civilization", "Harappan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Indus Valley Civilization or IVC"}, {"question": "A poster denouncing these people shows one being punched in the back by a giant fist, a reference to the origin of their name in the word for \u201cfist\u201d. The institutions that supplanted these people were protected from theft by the Law of the Spikelets. Hiring batrak laborers was one of the many, and often arbitrary, means of defining someone as one of these people. This class of people made up the largest portion of those executed during the (*) Great Purge. The persecution of these people was a major cause of the Holodomor and they were removed to make way for kolkhoz and sovkhoz collective farms. For 10 points, identify these relatively wealthy peasants deemed class enemies during Soviet agricultural collectivization.", "answer": "kulaks (prompt on class enemies or similar answers before giveaway)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>kulaks</u></b>", "acceptable": ["kulaks", "kulaks"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on class enemies or similar answers before giveaway"}, {"question": "Written in the Kawi Script by the King of Tondo, the Laguna Copperplate Inscription is the oldest known document found in this modern country. The Zhufan Zhi describes this modern country\u2019s trade with Song China and ethnically Chinese people here were known as sangley during its colonial period. This modern country was divided amongst numerous polities called barangays for much of its existence, a term deriving from the Austronesian word for \u201csailboat\u201d. Rajamuda Lumaya, a petty Chola prince, founded the Kingdom of (*) Cebu in this modern country, a polity more famously ruled by Humabon. The most famous European explorer of this modern country was killed by Lapu-Lapu\u2019s forces at the Battle of Mactan. For 10 points, this is what archipelago where Ferdinand Magellan died, now ruled from Manila?", "answer": "Philippines", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Philippines</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Philippines", "Philippines"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "During this battle, the Glengarry Light Infantry was forced to break off a flanking maneuver due to friendly fire. General Gordon Drummond ordered three failed frontal assaults on the enemy position during this engagement. Friendly fire happened again during this battle when Winfield Scott\u2019s forces were attacked by Americans. The British artillery was captured by (*) James Miller during this battle. After winning this battle, the Americans moved to Fort Erie, but the losses from the battle gave the British numerical supremacy in the region. Also called the Battle of Niagara Falls, for 10 points, name this bloody battle from the War of 1812 named after a road.", "answer": "Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane", "Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The first recorded earthquake occurred at Mt. Tai during this dynasty. This dynasty was interrupted by Han Zhuo, who later killed himself after losing a battle against Shao Kang. This dynasty was overthrown after the Battle of Mingtiao. A ruler of this dynasty apocryphally killed a nine-headed water monster that created swamps in its wake. A concubine of a ruler of this dynasty supposedly filled a lake with (*) wine and ordered 3,000 men to drink it dry. The most famous leader of this dynasty used \u201cself-expanding soil\u201d to stop a flood. This dynasty was founded by Yu the Great and the fall of this dynasty was the original justification for the Mandate of Heaven. For 10 points, what was this dynasty that supposedly preceded the Shang?", "answer": "Xia Dynasty", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Xia</u></b> Dynasty", "acceptable": ["Xia Dynasty", "Xia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A foreign advisor to the last ruler of this kingdom had the tree Nimloth chopped down and offered human sacrifices to a banished god of darkness and evil. A ruler of this kingdom established the port of Vinyalond\u00eb to solidify his burgeoning maritime empire, a move which strained his relationship with his queen Erendis. A successor state to this kingdom was rocked by the attempted usurpation of Castamir, the Kin-strife. Supported by the King\u2019s Men, Ar-Pharaz\u00f4n, the last king of this state, brought about its destruction by attacking the (*) Undying Lands, an event described in the Akallab\u00eath. The righteous Elendil escaped the downfall of this kingdom and his house founded the kingdoms of Arnor and Gondor. For 10 points, name this kingdom of Men, the dominant power of the Second Age of Middle-Earth.", "answer": "N\u00famenor (accept Elenna-n\u00f3r\u00eb or Westernesse)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>N\u00famenor</u></b>", "acceptable": ["N\u00famenor", "N\u00famenor"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Elenna-n\u00f3r\u00eb or Westernesse"}, {"question": "After following a trail of candy wrappers and soda bottles left by a rebel army, a nun was able to rescue 109 of 139 schoolgirls abducted from the St. Mary\u2019s College in Aboke in this country. To curb the influence of Christianity in a kingdom in this modern country and, as some accounts claim, punish some men who refused to have sex with him, King Mwanga II had the 55 \u201cMartyrs [of this country]\u201d executed. Alice Lakwena led the Holy Spirit Movement to bring an end to warfare in this country and redeem the (*) Acholi people of their war crimes. A military force in this country known for employing child soldiers seeks to create a Christian theocracy and was once funded by the nearby Sudanese government. The place of origin of the Lord\u2019s Resistance Army, for 10 points, identify this modern country home to Joseph Kony, Milton Obote, and Idi Amin.", "answer": "Uganda", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Uganda</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Uganda", "Uganda"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A leader of a city in this region is credited with inventing a flying device called \u201cThe Pigeon\u201d and is the namesake of a curve used to solve the doubling the cube problem. A famous athlete from this region apocryphally died when he became trapped by a tree he was trying to tear apart by hand and was eaten by wolves. Despite enlisting the aid of Hiero I of Syracuse, a city in this region was abandoned in the mid-5th century BCE and the city of Thurii was founded on roughly the same site shortly after. Tarquin the Proud died in exile in a city in this region. Cities in this region included (*) Kroton, Tarentum, the supposedly extravagant Sybaris, and the home of the most famous of the Sibyls, Cumae. For 10 points, identify this region of southern Italy named for its high number of settlers from across the Ionian Sea.", "answer": "Magna Graecia (accept Megale Hellas or [reluctantly] Great Greece; prompt on southern Italy)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Magna <b><u>Graecia</u></b> [reluctantly]", "acceptable": ["Magna Graecia", "Graecia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Megale Hellas or Great Greece; prompt on southern Italy"}, {"question": "An unimplemented plan sought to remove this politician from office by offering him a job running a television network. This politician defeated a man who claimed that \u201cyour home is your castle, protect it\u201d to become governor of his home state. Both his supporters and detractors wore watches with this man\u2019s face on them. This man was well-known for his colorful deprecations of opponents, such as (*) \u201cpusillanimous pussyfooters\u201d and \"nattering nabobs of negativism\". In his book Go Quietly\u2026or Else, this politician claimed that criminal charges brought against him were a conspiracy to distract from Watergate. For 10 points, name this first VP under Nixon who resigned due to tax evasion charges and who will one day reprise his highest office as a headless body.", "answer": "Spiro Agnew", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Spiro <b><u>Agnew</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Spiro Agnew", "Agnew"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "An occurrence of this practice in 1979 supposedly happened after the arrest of a group of schoolchildren protesting school uniforms. A form of this practice in Renaissance and Early Modern Europe used products from Egypt believed to have curative properties. George H. W. Bush was nearly involved in the Chichijima Incident, which included this practice. This practice was the end goal of the Leopard and Crocodile Societies of West Africa. The Korowai people maintain a (*) myth of engaging in this practice to promote tourism. This practice led to the prevalence of Kuru among the Fore people and charges of engaging in this practice were levied against Jean-B\u00e9del Bokassa. For 10 points, what is this practice, the consumption of members of one\u2019s own species?", "answer": "cannibalism (accept any answer that conveys people eating other people; prompt on murder or similar answers)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>cannibalism</u></b>", "acceptable": ["cannibalism", "cannibalism"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept any answer that conveys people eating other people; prompt on murder or similar answers"}, {"question": "Due to atrocities like hanging people alive to be eaten by animals and roasting children, a military unit traveling across this colony in 1898-1899 was labeled an \u201cinfernal column\u201d. Soldiers named after a portion of this colony were the fathers of the 16,000-18,000 \u201cRhineland Bastards\u201d. Only people born in the Four Communes of this colony were able to attain citizenship in its ruling country. The starting point of the Voulet-Chanoine Mission, most of the territorial expansion of this colony was done to forward the trade interests of the Maurel & Prom Company and was carried out by (*) Louis Faidherbe. After the dissolution of this colony, leaders like F\u00e9lix Houphou\u00ebt-Boigny and L\u00e9opold Senghor, among others, took power in the newly formed states. For 10 points, this was what colony, now split into 9 countries including Mauritania, Niger, and Mali?", "answer": "French West Africa (accept Afrique Occidentale Fran\u00e7aise or AOF; prompt on component colonies/their modern equivalents: Mali (French Sudan), Senegal, Guinea (French Guinea), Niger, Ivory Coast, Burkina Faso (Upper Volta), Togo, Benin (Dahomey), or Mauritania)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>French West Africa, Senegal, Guinea (French Guinea), Niger, Ivory Coast, Burkina Faso (Upper Volta), Togo, Benin (Dahomey), or Mauritania)</u></b>", "acceptable": ["French West Africa, Senegal, Guinea (French Guinea), Niger, Ivory Coast, Burkina Faso (Upper Volta), Togo, Benin (Dahomey), or Mauritania)", "French West Africa, Senegal, Guinea (French Guinea), Niger, Ivory Coast, Burkina Faso (Upper Volta), Togo, Benin (Dahomey), or Mauritania)"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Afrique Occidentale Fran\u00e7aise or AOF; prompt on component colonies/their modern equivalents: Mali (French Sudan"}, {"question": "A proliferation of Azolla ferns in the Arctic Ocean during this time period may have served as a massive carbon sink, drastically lowering worldwide temperatures. The anomalous Andrewsarchus lived during this time period and may be related to the Entelodonts, or \u201chell pigs\u201d, that first appeared during this epoch. The Wadi el Hitan in Egypt is famous for its marine-deposited rocks dating to this time period, which contain some of the earliest whales. Asteroid impacts at Popigai in Siberia and the Chesapeake Bay may have initiated the (*) mass extinction that ended this epoch. India began colliding with Asia during this epoch, closing the Tethys Sea. With the epoch before it, this epoch names a thermal maximum that raised temperatures 5-8\u00b0C. For 10 points, name this epoch, the second of the Paleogene period with a name referring to the \u201cdawn\u201d of many new mammalian orders.", "answer": "Eocene epoch", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Eocene</u></b> epoch", "acceptable": ["Eocene epoch", "Eocene"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A bronze sculpture of one of these objects was found with sculptures of a tiger, a water buffalo, and a rhino at Daimabad in 1974. The first known written mention of these items occurs on an inscription written on a dagger by the king of Kussara. Burials from the Sintashta Culture provide the first physical evidence for these items. In Bronze Age China, a state\u2019s power was ranked by the number of these items it possessed and they were frequently used in (*) royal hunts. The use of these items facilitated enough bloodshed \u201cto float a log\u201d at the Battle of Muye, but their most famous appearance in warfare was in a battle between Muwatalli II and Ramesses II. For 10 points, name these horse-drawn conveyances used en masse at the Battle of Kadesh.", "answer": "chariots", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>chariots</u></b>", "acceptable": ["chariots", "chariots"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable An early leader of this process apocryphally died while trying to cross a river because the armor given to him by his ruler was too heavy. One battle in this process saw the general Mametqul fail to use his cannons and the flight of Khan Kuchum to Bukhara. This process allowed for the katorga system and was consolidated by the construction of ostrogs at river confluences and portages, which aided the collection of yasak. An important expedition in this process was funded by the (*) Stroganov family and led to the fall of Qashliq to Yermak Timofeyevich after the Battle of Chuvash Cape. The spread of smallpox that accompanied this process devastated peoples like the Yukagir, Tungus, and Yakuts. For 10 points, what was this process that extended the borders of Russia to the Pacific Ocean?", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}